Guide to the George H. Sabine papers, [ca. 1886-1960]
Sabine, George H. papers, ca. 1886-1960
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
George H. Sabine papers, [ ca. 1886-1960 ]
14-21-547
George Holland Sabine, 1880-1961.
5 cubic ft.
Notes, drafts, correspondence, scrapbook.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Largely notes for and rough drafts of the revised edition of Sabine's chief work, A History of Political Theory, as well as additional books and correspondence.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Philosophy, dean of the Graduate School, and vice president of Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Largely notes for and rough drafts of the revised edition of Sabine's chief work, A History of Political Theory; supplemented by four books with underlining and marginal comments: A Treastise of Human Nature; After Utopia; Critique of Pure Reason; and What Is to Be Done. Includes reprints, book reviews, and examinations and other material pertaining to his professional life; a scrapbook (1900-1905) on his student days at Cornell; notes and correspondence concerning the publication of the diary of Cornell's first president, Andrew Dickson White; and genealogical papers on the Sabine family. Administrative and professional correspondence, and drafts and copies of Sabine's book reviews. Includes correspondence concerning Sabine's participation in the American Political Science Association. Correspondents include George Boas, Arthur C. Cole, Arthur H. Cole, Gustavus Watts Cunningham, Edmund Ezra Day, Dixon Ryan Fox, Ludwig F. Freund, George H. Gallup, Milton R. Konvitz, Harold J. Laski, Glenn R. Morrow, Frank Thilly, Charles M. Wiltse, and Carl F. Wittke.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sabine, George Holland, 1880-1961.; Boas, George, 1891-; Cole, Arthur Charles, 1886-; Cole, Arthur Harrison, 1889-; Cunningham, Gustavus Watts, 1881-; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Fox, Dixon Ryan, 1887-1945.; Freund, Ludwig Franz, 1898-; Gallup, George Horace, 1901-; Konvitz, Milton Ridvas, 1908-; Laski, Harold Joseph, 1893-1950.; Morrow, Glenn R. (Glenn Raymond), 1895-; Thilly, Frank, 1865-1934.; Wiltse, Charles Maurice, 1907-; Wittke, Carl Frederick, 1892-1971.; American Political Science Association.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University--Administration.; Cornell University. Dept. of Philosophy.; Cornell University. Graduate School.
Subjects:
Philosophy, Modern.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Cornell Law Quarterly, Mar. 1945 (Box 1)
- Journal of Philosophy, Nov. 9, 1933 (Box 1)
- Bulletin of the American Association of University Professors, Dec. 1929 (Box 1)
- Folder containing correspondence with Raymond P. Morse regarding William C. Pruyn 1903, check forger (Box 1)
- School and Society, Sept. 12, 1931 (Box 1)
- Lenin, V.I., What Is To Be Done? (Box 1)
- Packet of cards relating to membership in the "Royal Society" (Box 1)
- Kant, Critique of Pure Reason (Box 1)
- Shklar, After Utopia (Box 1)
- Hume, Treastise of Human Nature (Box 1)
- Family Genealogy within volume entitled "Record" (Box 1)
- International Journal of Ethics, Jan. 1926, Apr. 1927 (two issues) (Box 1)
- Yale Law Journal, Dec. 1940 (Box 1)
- Ethics, July 1938 (Box 1)
- Journal of Philosopy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, Nov. 25, 1915 (Box 1)
- Journal of Philosophy, June 4, 1931 (Box 1)
- Sabine, George H. (Box 1)
  "What is Political Theory?" reprint from the Journal of Politics, Feb. 1939
  "Radical Empiricism as a Logical Method" reprint from Philosophical Review, Nov. 1905
  "Professor Bosanquet's Logic and the Concrete Universal" reprint from PR, Sept. 1912
  "The Concept of the State as Power" reprint from PR, July 1920
  "Hume's Contribution to the Historical Method" reprint from PR, Jan. 1906
  "Bosanquet's Theory of the Real Will" reprint from PR, Nov. 1923 (2 copies)
  "Descriptive and Normative Sciences" reprint from PR, July 1912
  "Philosophical and Scientific Specialization" reprint from PR, Jan. 1917
  "The Concreteness of Thought" reprint from PR, Mar. 1907
  "The Pragmatic Approach to Political Science" reprint from American Political Science Review, Nov. 1930
  "Political Science and the Juristic Point of View" reprint from APSR, Aug. 1928
  "The Material of Thought" reprint from PR, May 1907
  "Henry Adams and the Writing of History" reprint from the University of California Chronical, Jan. 1924
- Vlastos, Gregory, "Equality and Justice in Early Greek Cosmologies" reprint from Classical Philology, July 1947 (Box 1)
- Review of Nesbit's The Quest for Community reprinted from the Southwestern Social Science Quarterly, June 1953 (Box 1)
- Sabine, G.H. (Box 1)
  "Democracy and Preconceived Ideas" Lecture delivered at Ohio State, May 1945
  "Logic and Social Studies" reprint from Philosophical Review, Mar. 1939
  Review of Irving Babbit Book Democracy and Leadership reprinted from University of California Chronical, Apr. 1925
  "Beyond Ideology" reprint from Philosophical Review, Jan. 1948
  "Social Studies and Objectivity" reprint from University of California Publications in Philosophy, 1941
  "Freedom and Reform" Philosophical Review, Sept. 1947
  "The Colloquium Heptaplomeres of Jean Bodin" reprint from "Persecution and Liberty"
- Personal Scrapbook from undergraduate days at Cornell (Box 1)
- The Utilitiarians: Palley, Betham, Mill, Austin (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Utilitiarianism: Seminary Notes - Bentham, Mill (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Political Theory - Mill, Green (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Political Theory - German Idealism (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Fascism (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Political Thought (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Contemporary Political Theory Notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Contemporary Political Theory Notes and Syllabus (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lectures: Recent Political Theory (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Scientific Method Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Scientific Method, Preliminary Reading List (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Scientific Method, Poincare, Eddington, Bridgman (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Scientific Method: Keynes, Ogden and Richards, Broad (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Types of Science, Course Notes (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Scientific Method, Illustrations (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Arts Survey (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Aristotle - Metaphysics A (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Aristotle - Metaphysics B (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Aristotle - Metaphysics TE (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Aristotle - Metaphysics Z, H (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Coherence (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Nicomachean Ethics (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Plotinus (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Berkeley (Box 1, Folder 24)
- R. Staminler (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Princeton Centennial (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Contemporary Political Theory (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Political Theory, Second Term, 1952-1953, Northwestern (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Political Theory, Fall Quarter, 1952, Northwestern (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Genealogical Material (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Memoirs of the National Academy of Sciences (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Smith (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Chapman Etchings (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "My Reminiscences of Ezra Cornell" (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Aristotle (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Culture (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Plato (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Memory (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Evolution (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "A Frenchman Who Remade the World" (Box 2, Folder 11)
- German Philosophy and the War (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "The Point of View of Idealism" (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "The Social Basis of Idealism" (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Types of Idealism" (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "The Prophets of Zwickau" (Box 2, Folder 16)
- The History of Modern Philosophy - References (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Syllabus - Elementary Ethics - Philosophy II (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Nietzsche: A Sentimental Individualist (Box 2, Folder 19)
- The Ethics of International Relations (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Administration, St. Lawrence University, Jan. 18, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Leninism (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Leites - Bolshevism (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Communism (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Marx (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Communism (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Marxism (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Marxism, Seminar 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Kant, Critique of Judgment (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Kant, Critique of Practcial Reason (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Political Theory, Exams (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Scheler-Wissenforman Erkenntnis and Arbeit (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Dewey - Quest for Certainty - copyright date, 1929, notes for Sabine's review (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Emil Lederer - The State of the Masses (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Notes: Gierke (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Bradley and Moore, Value Theory (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Latin Averroism Circle (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Ethics of Bolshevism (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Soviet of Science, NY Times, July 1959 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Mao, Djilas, "Criticism of Communism" (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Notes for Possible Lectures (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Leibniz (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Kant - Critique of Pure Reason (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Justice (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Logic and Social Studies, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Becker - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Russian-American Ideology, Prospects of Democracy, Creighton Club, Apr. 1947 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Charles A. Beard, Discussion of Human Affairs (Box 2, Folder 48)
- "Where Did Science Come From?" Research Club 1931 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Mannheim - Ideology and Utopia - Man and Society (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Notes: Objectivity and Social Studies (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Interests and Historical Evidence (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Marx (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Communism (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Notes on a Book (Box 3, Folder 3)
- An Episode of the Puritan Revolution (Box 3, Folder 4)
- From Status to Contract (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Conservatism, Rossiter, Kirk (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Berlin, Isaiah (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Winch - Peter (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Rawls - Justice as Fairness (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Hartz-Liberal Tradition (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Free Societies and Free Men (Box 3, Folder 11)
- G.A. de Laguna (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Lectures - Kluckholn, Kelly, Bidney, Mowter (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Riesman, Lonely Crowd, Morality to Morale (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Definitions of Culture (Box 3, Folder 15)
- T. Parsons - Theory of Action, Social Stratification (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Tonniew - Gemeinschaitt (Box 3, Folder 17)
- MacIver - Web of Government (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Whitehead - Adv. of Ideas (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Inkeles - Startification in Russia (Box 3, Folder 20)
- White - Organization Man (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Rawls - Two Concepts of Rules (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Ashley, Wildman, Becker (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Leibniz - Americana, Fichte - Americana (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Moral Communication (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Democracy - Rochester 1947 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Duverger - Poltical Parties (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Mills - White Collar, Warner - American Life (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Hart - Natural Law (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Historicism - Hegel (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Hart - Ascription, Waismann - Veritiability (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Morrow - Plato's Laws (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Chambers - Witness (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Party - Key, Hyneman (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Population - Notestein (Box 3, Folder 33)
- T.H. Green (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Denial of Metaphysics - Philosophy Club 1948 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Mead - Mind, Self, Society (Box 3, Folder 36)
- White Diary (Box 3, Folder 37)
- A.E. Murphy - On Practical Reason (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Lee - Language and Custom (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Mannheim, Leites (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Sapir - Cultural Anthropology and Psychiatry (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Dollard - Frustration and Aggresion, Minorities - Colonial Administration, Murrag - Personality (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Toulmin - Reason in Ethics (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Role Personality - Whorf, Pritchard, Newcomb, Merton, F. Kluckholn (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Toynbee (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Conant - Science and Common Sense, English Marxist (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Ginsberg, Malinowdki, Lasswell, Benedict, Horney, Mead, Musdock (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Herring - Politics of Democracy, Hogben-Retreat from Reason, Dennis-Dynamics of War (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Dewey - Logic; Criticism of Dewey's Philosophy (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Spanish Arcitecture (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Howism Lecture (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Eugene 1950 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Irrationalism (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Reviews and Letters (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Sutton, Winstanley (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Leighton, Lynd, Frank, Sherif (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Northrup - Meeting of East and West, Ideological Man (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Digger Biography (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Personal Psycology (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Liberalism (Box 3, Folder 60)
- De Tocqueville (Box 3, Folder 61)
- Natural Law (Box 3, Folder 62)
- Papper - Open Society, Historicism (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Ideological Conflict, Industrial College of the Armed Forces (Box 3, Folder 64)
- The Ideological Conflict in the Struggle for Power (Box 3, Folder 65)
- The Law of Nature (Box 3, Folder 66)
- DeLaguna Lecture (Box 3, Folder 67)
- James Burnham (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Social Science Research Center (Box 3, Folder 69)
- Banking Records (Box 3, Folder 70)
- Max Weber - Wissinchaftslchre (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Democrary and Preconceived Ideas (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Reading Notes (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Political Theory - Fact and Value (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Papers on Fact, Value Dialectic (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Scientific Method and the New Physics (Box 4, Folder 6)
- The Liberal Arts College (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Bodin-Heptaplomeres (Box 4, Folder 8)
- The Proletarian Movement (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Lilburne and Cromwell (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Ethical Theory (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Ancient Philosophy (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Syllabus, History of Philosophy (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Logic (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Nature of Political Theory (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Political Theory - The Greek City State (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Political Theory - Pre-Platonic (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Political Theory - Plato (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Plato - The Laws (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Estate of Wilfred S. Sabine (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Political Theory - Aristotle (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Political Theory - Post-Aristotelian to Polybins (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Political Theory - The Roman Lawyers (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Political Theory - Cicero Seneca (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Political Theory - Cicero (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Cicero Outline (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Political Theory - 9th Century Feudalism (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Political Theory - 10th and 12th Centuries (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Political Theory - Middle Ages - Church and Empire (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Political Theory - St. Thomas Aquinas (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Phillip the Fair and Boniface VIII (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Political Theory - Marsiglio and Conciliaris ts (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Political Theory - Rise of Nations - Machiavelli (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Political Theory - The Reformers - Luther and Calvin (Box 4, Folder 34)
- The Monarchomachs (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Divine Right of Man (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Jean Bodin (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Althusis (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Political Theory - Grotius (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Bacon (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Political Theory - England 16th Century (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Diggers (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Political Theory - Milton (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Harrington (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Filmer (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Halifax (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Political Theory - Locke (Box 4, Folder 47)
- England - 18th Century (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Descartes (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Hume (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Germany - 18th Century (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Rousseau (Box 4, Folder 52)
- France - 18th Century, Montesquieu and Helvitus (Box 4, Folder 53)
- French Revolution (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Hume and Burke (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Fascism (Box 4, Folder 56)
- French Reaction, Bonold, DeMaistre(?) (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Political Theory - Hobbes (Box 4, Folder 58)
- Levellers (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Letters A-Z, 1940-1943 (Box 5)
- Letters A-Z, 1946-1948 (Box 5)
- Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association, 1937-1943 (Box 6)
- Advisory Committee to the Collection of Regional History, 1947 (Box 6)
- Committee on Research, 1947 (Box 6)
- Kallen Festschrift, 1945-1947 (Box 6)
- Encyclopedia Britannica, 1946 (Box 6)
- Winstanley Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 6)
- Textbook Committee, American Committee for Democracy and Intellectual Freedom, 1941-1942 (Box 6)
- History of Political Theory (Box 6)
- Milton Konvitz, 1945-1946 (Box 6)
- Book Reviews, 1940-1950 (Box 6)
- Amercian Political Science Association, Nomination Committee, 1948 (Box 7)
- Correspondence relating to Maximilian Beck, 1947 (Box 7)
- Burr Volume (Box 7)
- Correspondence relating to The William P. Chapman Print Collection (Box 7)
- Coulburn Correspondence (Box 7)
- Committee on Classification of Universities and Colleges, Associatioof American Universities (Box 7)
- Cresswell Correspondence (Box 7)
- Review - H.R.G. Greaves, The Foundation of Political Theory (Box 7)
- Lectures away from Cornell; Invitations; Conferences, 1937-1943 (Box 7)
- Lectures of Recommendation (Box 7)
- Paine, E.T. - Reappointment, 1935-1936 (Box 7)
- Morrow Correspondence (Box 7)
- Pulitzer Prize Jury (Box 7)
- Winstanley - Reviews and Letters of Comment on the Book Itself (Box 7)